Good morning everybody חג פורים
שמח. Chag Purim Sameach. I'll start with a joke in honor of
פורים. Purim. Scholar-in-residence goes into a synagogue and he's going to synagogue
for שבת Shabbos and before שבת Shabbos the rabbi is showing him
around, brings him into the sanctuary, and he says, "Now remember, when
you give your talk, speak very loudly. This synagogue has horrible agnostics."
I ruined it. "Remember, when you give your talk, speak very loudly.
The synagogue has horrible agnostics."
Alright,
anyway, so that's your פורים Purim Torah.
Alright, anyway, thank you, even though I little flubbed the punchline, but
okay, anyway.
Alright, now
so now the גמרא Gemara says, "Alright, so on the משנה Mishna
about this famous story about the bathhouse of Aphrodites," and he gave
him all these answers and he says, he says, "Oh, can't talk
in a bathhouse." By the way, I think that the answer, "can't
talk in a bathhouse," is also a little bit like a שידוך
shidduch because he's like saying like, "this place is so like," not
disgraceful, I mean, you know, whatever, you're just bathing or whatever, but
so inappropriate for holy matters that I can't even like respond to
you in a תורה Torah matter, you know, and and you want
to tell me that it somehow is connected ritually to עבודה זרה?
Avodah Zarah? Like you know, it heightens the point that this is
a the most inappropriate of places, which is sort of the point
at the end, you know, people urinate in front of it and
you're going to tell me that this is a type of related
to an עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? You need those types of things
you show honor to. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says תשובה גנובה
השיבו, tshuvah gnuva heishivo,
that he gave him an incomplete answer. Now רש"י Rashi says it
means he gave him like a, you know, like a throwaway answer
and it because it wasn't really a valid answer. That would mean
that the answer he gave him really wasn't a strong enough answer.
But the גמרא Gemara is going to continue and actually say that
the answer he gave him actually there was even stronger points to
make. So it doesn't mean just like it was like a fake
answer. The way תוספות Tosfos reads it, it means it was an
incomplete answer, you know, it wasn't a fully explicated answer is the
way תוספות Tosfos explains it. Okay, so we pick up with that.
So where are we exactly? אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye,
so the גמרא Gemara gave a few reasons why it could have
been a better answer, okay. אמר אביי גנובתא דהכא, Amar Abaye gnuvta
d'hacha,
the way it was like incomplete is based on the following way,
דאמר ליה אני לא באתי בגבולה והיא באה בגבולי. d'amar leh ani
lo bati bigvula v'hi ba bigvuli. He says, "Look, I I didn't
come into its zone, it came into my zone." This place was
first a bathhouse and then, no, it means it's first a bathhouse,
then you bring the idol in, so the idol isn't going to
change the status of the bathhouse, you know, you don't have the
right to change it. Now actually that's going to tie into the
next משנה, Mishna, like just because I worship something, I mean the
question is, is it mine or not mine? If it's my house
and I bring an idol into it, it's one thing. If it's
a public space and I bring an idol into it, now if
the public owns the bathhouse and the public is bringing the idol
into it, maybe it can change it. But you know, that's a
question of what can I do through my acts to change something
that I don't own, that's partly ish. There's also an issue which
is going to be tied into the next משנה, Mishna, which is
something that is attached to the ground מחובר לקרקע, mechuber l'karka,
you know, and to what degree, if you build a house as
a base of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah it's one thing, but to
what degree if something is already a house and like you're now
bringing your idol into it, can you change its identity? Because the
more something is part of the ground or attached to the ground,
the less it's seen as like it's something that's, you know, sort
of under human control and definition and so on, it's just part
of the landscape, you know, so therefore that's that's seems to be
part of the answer. Okay, so that was the answer. "Look, it
the bathhouse was here first, you don't bring an idol in and
therefore change its status," והיא באה בגבולי. v'hi ba bigvuli. וכי באה
בגבולה מאי הוי? v'chi ba bigvula mai havi?
So the גמרא Gemara says, "And but the גמרא Gemara says like
you look, you know, you can even make a stronger point that
even if you initially was a was a bathhouse for Aphrodites, it
wasn't that first it was the bathhouse and then Aphrodite was brought
in. It initially was that way." So why should that make a
difference? It still shouldn't really be a problem. והתנן, v'hatnan, we taught
a משנה Mishna עבודת כוכבים שיש למרחץ avodas kochavim sheyesh l'merchatz או
גינה, o gina, if you have an idol that has in front
of it a bathhouse or a garden, and that means it was
originally constructed for that sake to be connected to the idol, נהנין
מהן שלא בטובה nehenin mehen shelo b'tova ואין נהנין בהן בטובה. v'ein
nehenin bahen b'tova. You can benefit from it as long as you
don't do it through any sort of sense of thanking the priests
and showing gratitude and so on, but it's not איסורי הנאה. isurei
hana'ah. The איסור issur would be as a way of expressing thanks
and gratitude, but the איסור issur would not be it doesn't become
אסור בהנאה. asur b'hana'ah. But you cannot do it with that thanks
and gratitude. ואני אומר v'ani omer and אביי Abaye says אינה גנובה,
eina gnuva, "No, actually it's not an incomplete answer. Actually that point,
had it started off as a bathhouse of Aphrodites, it really would
be a problem." Why? Aren't you allowed to get benefit from it
שלא בטובה? shelo b'tova?
So I say no, שלא בטובת רבן גמליאל כטובת אחרים דמי. shelo
b'tovas Rabban Gamliel k'tovas acheirim dami. It's so an honor to have
Rabban Gamliel come and visit our bathhouse that that is like other
people's gratitude and therefore it would have been a problem had it
started off as a bathhouse for Aphrodites. Now why is it that
if it started off as a bathhouse or as a garden are
you allowed to derive benefit? So if you take a look at
רש"י, Rashi, right, look at רש"י Rashi says וכי באה בגבולה v'chi
ba bigvula רש"י Rashi כלומר ואפילו קדמה עבודת כוכבים למרחץ מאי איכפת
ליה. klomar v'afilu kadma avodas kochavim l'merchatz mai ichpat leh.
so what would it have mattered? Because don't we have this משנה
Mishna שלא בטובה, shelo betovah, שלא יחזיק טובה לכומרים, shelo yachzik tovah
lachomarim,
don't sort of be grateful to the priest, ובהנאה לא מיתסר, uve'hana'ah
lo mityaser, but it's not forbidden to הנאה. hana'ah. כי אמרינן לקמן
אין הקדש לעבודת כוכבים עד שיקריב לפניו בתקרובת. Ki amrina lekaman ein
hekdesh l'avodat kochavim ad sheyakriv lefanav bitkroves. Just because something is built
to be connected to an עבודה זרה avodah zarah now that gets
to these interesting questions. What are the different ways things can be
forbidden בהנאה? bahana'ah? One is you worship it, an עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. The other is נוי עבודה זרה, noy avodah zarah, something you
put on it in order to adorn it. The other is תקרובת
עבודה זרה, tikroves avodah zarah, something that you actually go ahead and
you offer it up to it. But what about מרקוליס? Merkulis?
I thought if you're עובד מרקוליס oved Merkulis is there תקרובת tikroves
for that? Like at least the גמרא Gemara viewed it as you
throw rocks there.
Yes, that's a תקרובת tikroves type of
that'd be תקרובת tikroves type of תקרובת.
tikroves. Something it's an act of yeah, I mean that's always the
question of exactly how you define it. You know, and then there's
תשמישי עבודת כוכבים, tashmishei avodat kochavim, things that sort of are appendages
to it, servant, appurtenances as I think the word. Anyway, and all
these things, the question is what type of use and what puts
them in this category to be a problem. So רש"י Rashi here
says, I mean this is what we're going to be focusing on
now, so we can't sort of fully flesh this out. But if
you look at רש"י Rashi says, אין הקדש לעבודת כוכבים עד שיקריב
לפניו בתקרובת. ein hekdesh l'avodat kochavim ad sheyakriv lefanav bitkroves. This garden,
even if I designate it, this is the garden of Aphrodite, I'm
going to put an Aphrodite statue here and designate this as Aphrodite's
garden. Okay, the words that I'm designating it don't make it, you
know, sanctified, quote unquote, don't make it connected to the עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. It was the garden wasn't offered as a type of
a sacrifice, as an offering. It's not something physically on the idol
that adorns it. Now the question is why isn't it תשמישי עבודה
זרה, tashmishei avodah zarah, right? And, you know, and something that's there
to sort of be a way of appurtenance to it. And, you
know, is it because these things were connected to the ground already
and therefore all words if I built the מרחץ merchatz for the
sake of Aphrodite, right, why wouldn't that be like a type of
a תשמישי עבודה זרה? tashmishei avodah zarah? So רש"י Rashi is not
fully clear about that point. But anyway, that's the basic point, that
these things are not you didn't do enough with it to connect
it to the עבודה זרה avodah zarah even if it started off
that way. Okay, and the שלא בהנאה shelo behana'ah is and if
you look at the רש"י Rashi about שלא בטובה shelo betova which
just says כטובת אחיו עם רבן גמליאל שהיה חשוב וטובה היא להם
כשנהנה מהם. ke'tovos achiv im Rabban Gamliel shehaya chashuv vetova hi lahem
keshenehaneh mehem. That's like doing a favor to them for him to
visit their bathhouse. הלכך אי לאו מרחץ קודם הוה אסור כל הני.
Hilkach ilav merchatz kodem hava assur kol hani. If it wasn't for
that the מרחץ merchatz was first, it actually would have been a
problem because then if it really would have been defined as a
מרחץ merchatz of Aphrodite. Now it's not a מרחץ merchatz of Aphrodite.
Now it's the public מרחץ merchatz that has a statue of Aphrodite.
But had the Aphrodite statue come first and it had been defined
as a מרחץ merchatz of Aphrodite, even though it wouldn't be אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'ah, the use of it would be a way of
showing honor to the priest or whatever, to Aphrodite and so on,
and therefore it would have been a problem. Yes, Charlie?
Practical application if you think Christianity is עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. The
town greens in most New England communities
started out and in most cases are still owned by the local
church. Right.
So that does become all of those types of questions, exactly. And
here the basic point is that it's not a problem, although the
question is how do you define בטובה. betovah. And then that's an
important discussion that תוספות Tosafos has. Because תוספות Tosafos says many, many
שלא בטובה. shelo betovah. תוספות Tosafos says might actually mean that that
you can do it without paying, but you can't actually pay. And
if you pay to get in and then that money goes to
the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, and then that's a different it's not
just saying thank you or not. Yeah, but I can rent an
apartment that's owned by... I know. Anyway, תוספות Tosafos right, we're not
talking about that. But that's specifically associated like Aphrodite's bathhouse, okay? So
תוספות Tosafos has that whole question.
If you go into an ashram, you know, where they want to
just do yoga or meditate and some people in there I've told
like may bow to to an image of something. So if you're
not bowing down to that then it's then you it's okay to
go in there?
Yeah, so that does also become a question of exactly that, as
to what degree is a place that is now this is different.
This is a bathhouse. This at the end of the day is
something that's there to make the grounds nice for the עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, but it's not actually the place of worship of the
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So a place of worship for the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah is more closely connected and then it does get
to this question of איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah. Is going in, getting
הנאה, hana'ah, this aesthetic הנאה, hana'ah, going and getting הנאה? hana'ah? So
obviously those are all those relevant questions. I don't want to get
into them. One minute, I just want to look quickly at תוספות
Tosafos because we have a whole other דף daf we gotta finish.
Anyway, תוספות Tosafos says if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, ועוד נראה
לרבינו תם, ve'od nira le'Rabbeinu Tam, it's about 10 lines before the
lines get wide. ועוד נראה לרבינו תם דמה שאנו אופים עתה בתנור
של כומרים וטוחנים בריחיים של מים שלהם, ve'od nira le'Rabbeinu Tam d'ma
she'anu ofim ata betanur shel komrim vetochunim bereichayim shel mayim shelahem, I
always love the ones that talk about their historical reality, you know.
ועוד נראה לרבינו תם דמה שאנו אופים עתה בתנור של כומרים וטוחנים
בריחיים של מים שלהם, ve'od nira le'Rabbeinu Tam d'ma she'anu ofim ata
betanur shel komrim vetochunim bereichayim shel mayim shelahem,
we now use, you know, the monastery's ovens, you know, they had
these big bread ovens, and we use their mills, okay. ודאי ליכא
למיחש. vadai leka lemichash.
It's not a problem. דלא מיבעיא בשכר דשרי, d'lo mibaya besachar desharei,
first of all, when you pay and one read of שלא בטובה
shelo betovah is only if you do it for free, you can't
pay. דאיננו מחזיקים להם טובה אלא אפילו ella afilu דאינם מחזיקים להם
טובה. Because the question is, is it worse or better when you
pay? If you pay you could say it's better because on the
one hand, ah, it's... transactional. I'm not on the other hand, maybe
your money is going to contribute to that cause. So this does—this
is saying that actually if you pay it's better. Okay? So first
of all, if we pay, דאין אנו מחזיקים להם טובה, de-ein anu
machzikim lahem tova, then we're not grateful to them, it's transactional. אלא
ella wait,
wait, wait, אלא אפילו I lost my place. אלא אפילו שלא בשכר
נמי מותר ella afilu shelo beschar nami mutar כיון שאינו נתון ועומד
חיים בבית עבודת כוכבים עצמו keivon she-eino natun ve-omed chaim be-veis avodas
kochavim atzmo כמו הכא המרחץ של אפרודיטי kemo hacha ha-merchatz shel Afroditi
ולא דמי ל v'lo dami l okay
then he goes on and on. Okay? And he says also it's
better because it's like, you know, they own it, it's their property,
it's church property, but that doesn't mean that it's actually directly connected
to, you know, their house of worship or their objects of worship
and so on. Okay?
So even if it's—even if it's in a separate building?
Yeah, the church, the local monastery owns the mill, they own the
ovens, it's not directly...
But what if it's like a room in the bottom of the
church?
Yeah, then that might be that could be more that theoretically could
be more problematic. Right. Okay, so back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
רב שימי בר חייא אמר Rav Shimi bar Chiya amar גנובתא מהכא.
genuvta me-hacha.
No,
the reason it was an incomplete answer was the following: דקאמר לה
זו עומדת על הביב וכל אדם משתין
בפניה. de-ka'amar lah zo omedes al ha-beev ve-chol adam mashtin be-faneha. This
Aphrodite's standing by the pipe and all people are urinating in front
of it. וכי משתין בפניה מאי הוי. ve-chi mashtin be-faneha mai havei.
So so what? What do you mean that urinating is a sign
that they don't treat it as a god? והתנן רק בפניה השתין
בפניה גירר וזרק בה את הצואה הרי זו אינה בטלה. ve-hatnan rak
be-faneha hishtin be-faneha girer ve-zarak bah es ha-tzoa harei zo einah betelah.
If a non-Jew were supposed to spat at his idol, urinated on
his idol, or dragged it or threw excrement at it, that's not
a ביטול bitul of the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, well we're
going to see in a minute. So ביטול עבודה זרה bitul avodah
zarah has to do with like breaking something off, maybe flattening it,
and doing a physical change to it. But just doing acts of
disgust or acts of, you know, of denigrating it without actually physically
changing it is not a ביטול. bitul. So if the Aphrodite was
a real עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, the fact that people are urinating
is not a symbol that it is a ביטול. bitul. ואני אומר
ניסא אינה גנובה. ve-ani omer nisa einah genuvah. No, it's not that
it's not a—it's not an incomplete answer or a bad answer. התם
לפי שעה הוא רתח עליה והדר מפייס לה. hatam lefi sha'ah hu
rasach aleha ve-hadar me-fayes lah. There,
you know, it's like when a kid gets upset, "Oh you're the
worst mommy in the world," and you kick your parent or whatever,
and then you make up. Okay, fine. So you got angry and
then you made up. It's not a ביטול, bitul, doesn't really want
to, just wants to, you know, you want to express your anger.
Okay? הכא hacha and then you make up. הכא כל שעתא ושעתא
בבזיונה קיימא. hacha kol sha'ata ve-sha'ata be-vizyoneh kaymah. Here,
consistently you're urinating in front of it, this is the way it's
used, so that obviously shows that you don't really treat it as
an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
There's actually רב Rav משה פיינשטיין Moshe Feinstein was asked once about
going into churches because for to vote, because you know, like here
sometimes at the HJR, they have voting like that where you have
big public spaces, you know, and if depending on how you think
of a church, בית עבודה זרה, beis avodah zarah, whatever blah blah
blah. Anyway, so I don't think I read this inside, somebody told
me this that he, like, that it was בעל פה, ba'al peh,
I'm not sure. Anyway, he said, since that since they actually are
bringing the whole thing about this, about the HJR, since they're actually
bringing all of this whole voting stuff into the church, that's like
a ביטול bitul because obviously you're not treating the space as holy
space if you're doing voting in it. Of course, it's pretty funny
because, you know, maybe he felt just for at least for the
period while the voting stuff was there, it was considered like a
type of a ביטול. bitul. Anyway, so here, certainly not long term,
look at what the גמרא Gemara says about throwing excrement on it.
Anyway, okay, רבה בר עולא אמר Rabba bar Ulla amar גנובתא מהכא.
genuvta me-hacha. The reason it was not a great answer—it was not
a full answer—was from here: דקאמר ליה אינו אומר נעשה מרחץ נוי
לאפרודיטי אלא נעשה אפרודיטי נוי למרחץ. de-ka'amar leh eino omer na'aseh merchatz
noy le-Afroditi ella na'aseh Afroditi noy le-merchatz. I always felt that that
was the best answer. You know, it's not that we're going to
create a bathhouse to honor this statue of Aphrodite. No, we've got
a bathhouse and let's bring in an Aphrodite statue, that'll look nice.
So even if the Aphrodite was עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, the bathhouse
is not a תשמיש tashmish of the Aphrodite, the Aphrodite is a
תשמיש tashmish of the bathhouse. This actually becomes very important for the
whole discussion about sanctuaries and the church and so on. That even
if you consider the statues a type of an object of worship,
okay, you know, in it's not like, you know, when they had
a temple of Zeus that they create—the center was the statue and
the temple was built around it to sort of serve it. Here,
no, you know, it's the sanctuary's the primary place of worship and
prayer and whatever, and then they bring in those statues, you know,
to add to it, right? So it's like what is the nature
of the relationship? Okay, so, okay. וכי אמר נעשה מרחץ לאפרודיטי נוי
מאי הוי. ve-chi amar na'aseh merchatz le-Afroditi noy mai havei.
Now this goes back to the earlier point about the—about the—about the
גינו gino or the מרחץ, merchatz, that even if you לכתחילה lechatchila
wanted to make this to be, you know, to be an adornment
for the Aphrodite, why would that make it forbidden? Okay? Yes, there
is this category of נוי עבודה זרה, noy avodah zarah, but would
it really apply to something like this, something that's like attached to
the ground? Okay, מאי הוי והתניא האומר בית לעבודת כוכבים כותל לעבודת
כוכבים לא אמר כלום. mai havei ve-hatanya ha-omer bayis le-avodas kochavim kosel
le-avodas kochavim lo amar klum.
If you just say, you know, that's the same like line the
גמרא Gemara used before, אין הקדש לעבודת זרה. ein hekdesh le-avodah zarah.
If you just designate it, that's not enough.
Okay, now of course that's if you just designate it, but let's
say you built it with that intent, maybe that would be different.
ואני אומר v'ani omer אין גנובה ein genuva דהא דאיצטרי למיצרי deha
d'itztrei l'mitzrei נוי מיהא איכא. noy miha ika.
It might not be forbidden, but it still is נוי. noy. Now
that seems a little circular. You said it's not a problem, and
then you said it's still נוי. noy. So what does this mean?
So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, look רש"י Rashi again says
אין הקדש לעבודת כוכבים ein hekdesh l'avodas kochavim באמירה ba'amira עד שיקריבנה
לפניה בתיקרובת, ad sheyakrivena lefaneha b'tikroves,
like we said before, you have to bring it as an offering.
Okay, so then what's the reason at the end that it would
be a problem, right? So again this עד שיקריבנה לפניה בתיקרובת ad
sheyakrivena lefaneha b'tikroves נוי מיהא איכא noy miha ika אי הוי מרחץ
נוי לעבודת כוכבים אסור ליהנות מעבודת כוכבים אף על גב דאיצורי לא
מצר מרחץ בהנאה.
ei havay merchatz noy l'avodas kochavim assur l'ehannos me'avodas kochavim af al
gav d'itzurei lo
mitzra merchatz bahana'ah.
רש"י Rashi says an interesting point. Not that בחפצא, b'cheftza, to use
Brisker language, that the מרחץ merchatz would be considered a נוי noy
for the Aphrodites if the Aphrodites came first. Okay, no, it would
not be connected to the Aphrodites as an object that it's forbidden
to get benefit from. But then if that was the structure, then
the act of bathing would be considered a way of showing honor
to Aphrodites, and the problem would be the act of bathing, not
deriving benefit from the bathhouse, but the act of bathing. That's what
רש"י Rashi says.
Except that this isn't a problem here, right?
Right, so that's what he says, but that's why it's אינה גנובה.
eina genuva. But the first answer was that even if, you know
what, it was an incomplete answer because even if it had been
the reverse, it wouldn't have been a problem because the מרחץ merchatz
wouldn't have been אסור בהנאה assur bahana'ah even if it had been
made for the sake of Aphrodites. And the answer is, well, no,
that would have been a problem because the מרחץ merchatz might not
be אסור בהנאה, assur bahana'ah, but you still wouldn't be allowed to
bathe there because it would be showing honor. One minute. תוספות Tosafot
again, this is all very important and it's going to lead into
the next דף daf because it's all this question about when does
something become attached to an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So תוספות Tosafot
says וכי נעשה מרחץ נוי לעבודת כוכבים מאי הוי
v'chi na'asah merchatz noy l'avodas
kochavim mai havay וקשיא דלעיל אמרנו דנוי ותכשיט דעבודת כוכבים אסורין. v'kashya
d'le'eil amarnu d'noy v'tachshit d'avodas kochavim assurin. Okay, what do you mean
what is it? It might be your words don't make something connected
to the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but actually using something as a
type of adornment does do it. So למעשה, l'ma'aseh, if you're actually
using it as a type of an adornment, it's like we had
the discussion before. Why isn't it a נוי? noy? Why isn't it
a תכשיט? tachshit? Why isn't it a, what they call, you know,
a תשמיש? tashmish? ומה שמשני נוי מיהא איכא. u'mah shemeshani noy miha
ika. I mean, that seems a little circular. So then he says,
okay, I'm going to skip you to the punchline.
If you see three lines from the bottom, the word starting with
דודאי. d'vadai. דודאי נוי ותכשיט לעבודת כוכבים לא הוי. d'vadai noy v'tachshit
l'avodas kochavim lo havay. This is not a technical נוי. noy. Why
not if it's used for that purpose? לא הוי האי מרחץ לאסור
כדין נוי דעבודת כוכבים ותכשיטיה lo havay hai merchatz l'assur k'din noy
d'avodas kochavim v'tachshiteha אלא כדין בית. ela k'din bayis. Okay, that it's
just it's a, wait a minute, does he actually say why? One
minute.
אלא כדין בית ela k'din bayis ומסיק, u'masik, meaning the גמרא Gemara
initially thought let's not say this is forbidden as a נוי עבודה
זרה, noy avodah zarah, let's say it's forbidden as a בית של
עבודה זרה. bayis shel avodah zarah. And then it said, oh no,
but a בית, bayis, that doesn't become אסור assur just by your
words and saying this בית bayis should be for עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. So then the answer is, the punchline answer is,
okay, you know what, this תוספות Tosafot doesn't spell it out so
much. Anyway, I'll just tell you it doesn't spell out exactly, but
in the end, תוספות Tosafot says that it really is אסור assur
as נוי, noy, okay, at least rabbinically. So to just pull back,
I'm sorry I got you a little confused there. To just pull
back, this is going to be very important going forward because the
גמרא Gemara says here if it had been that it started with
Aphrodites at the center, right, would that still have made this אסור
assur as a type of a נוי noy or a תשמיש עבודה
זרה? tashmish avodah zarah? The גמרא Gemara really looked at that twice,
right, a few lines above and now again. And the basic answer
is no, you know, in the end that wouldn't have been a
problem, like a בית, bayis, you know, it's אין הקדש לעבודת כוכבים.
ein hekdesh l'avodas kochavim. A מרחץ merchatz in front of an עבודה
זרה avodah zarah is not a problem, a garden is not, a
בית bayis is not by words, etc. So the question at the
end is like, but why not? Like why isn't that a נוי?
noy? Why isn't that a תכשיט? tachshit? Why isn't that a תשמיש?
tashmish? The גמרא Gemara never fully explains, it's not just your words.
If you actually are making it to adorn the עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, to beautify it, why not? So it's not fully explicated here,
but I would say that there's a couple of things to be
thinking about. Number one is that it's not like something that's like
gold and silver that you put on it. It's just grounds in
front of it. Okay, and that might be too removed from direct
connection to the physical item to be considered connected to it. Okay,
everybody get that point? Meaning a normal thing is, you know, I
put something on top, this is my little idol, and I'm going
to drape jewelry over it, okay, and things that are going to,
you know, if I just have grounds, it's too physically distant and
it's not something directly physically connected. That's one reason why it might
not be enough. And the other reason is that things that are
attached to the ground are part of the landscape. They're not things
that I can define. You know, I don't have the ability to
give them their meaning, and that's really going to be the next
משנה. mishnah. Now, the difference of those two answers is let's say
I actually construct it with that in mind. It's not like I
just have a מרחץ merchatz here and I designate it. I'm digging
and cementing and creating the מרחץ merchatz for the purpose of creating
an Aphrodite מרחץ. merchatz. So that I really do have control over,
okay? Okay, so and nevertheless from this גמרא Gemara it sounds like
that that technically would not create a problem. Somehow it's still too
unrelated to the thing that it never really becomes a נוי noy
or a תשמיש של עבודה זרה. tashmish shel avoda zara. Okay, so
this is important in terms of what type of connection you need.
Is it, was it a טיבה גנובה, tiva gnuva, was it not
a טיבה גנובה? tiva gnuva? But it never fully explicates like why
even though exactly why yes, why no.
If I understand, so for Christianity or any syncretic faith, if you
build, the church is the...
Yeah, so a בית עבודה זרה beis avoda zara is a separate
issue that we're going to get to and all of those are
related. Right? I mean, the question came before as well, you know,
when David was asking about this shrine and so on. Right? So
if that's really true, if the garden in front of it and
the מרחץ merchatz in front of it is not, what about the
actual בית, bayis, you know, room that directly serves it? Obviously that's
more closely connected. And yes, a בית עבודה זרה beis avoda zara
is a problem. But it's exactly going to be figuring out like
what are the differences. But we... Okay, we haven't... well, there's still
the rest of the מסכת maseches to learn. Okay, yes, Charlie?
Well, we still have the rest of the מסכת maseches to learn,
but this is another example that I've mentioned that we pay more
attention to what our viewpoint is rather than what the עובדי כוכבים
ovdei kochavim are...
Right, well, we have to fill it in... I mean, there's always
that question. You know, we have to create our הלכה halachic constructs
of what type of a connection is relevant, but then we also
get to have to get the facts straight and find out from
them how do they really perceive the relationship? Okay? Meaning they can
tell us how they perceive the relationship, then we have to figure
out what legal boxes to put it in. Okay, no, let's move
on, okay? All right. Next משנה. Mishna. הנכרים... Hanochrim... this is very
interesting that the משנה Mishna starts with הנכרים Hanochrim and it hasn't
been edited to say like העכו"ם, Ha-akum, okay? הנכרים העובדים... Hanochrim ha'ovdim...
I don't know why, because this is not a focus on our
attitude towards them, it's a focus on the objects of worship. Thanks.
That's הגוים. Hagoyim. הגוים. Goyim. All right, that's... I don't know if
הנכרים Hanochrim or הגוים Goyim if that's if that was censored or
if those are two... anyway, הנכרים העובדים... Hanochrim ha'ovdim...
Well, we weren't worried the Christians were worshipping?
Well, I do want to say actually, let me use this as
a moment to say something since I wasn't here for the beginning
of the פרק perek and I think I've mentioned this before, but
it's worth repeating, which is we read through all this stuff about
עבודה זרה, avoda zara, right? And the whole beginning is just about
like what our interactions with them and are we exposing ourselves to
danger, are we supporting their worship. Then we got to all this
issue about food. Now we're talking to things about like the real
idols and the objects of worship and so on. But with all
this, the whole focus is, are these things forbidden בהנאה? bahana'ah? Are
we allowed to get benefit from them? Right? What's missing from the
entire discussion, and scholars have pointed this out, is, and we're going
to get to it a little bit today but just in passing,
not as a real discussion, is our obligation to go and destroy
it. Right? You know, you read the פסוקים psukim in דברים Devarim
and in שמות, Shmos, whatever, like, go in and destroy their idols
and cut down the trees and... it's very, very, like, I mean
almost like the biggest repeating theme in the תורה Torah other than
שבת Shabbos maybe, is destroy all their idols and destroy all their
places of worship. Okay? And that's completely absent. And part of the
reason is is that you're living in as a minority religion, you
know, in a dominant culture whatever that is pagan and so on,
it is not helpful for anyone to talk about your obligation, you
know, to go ahead and destroy it. Even to say technically we're
obligated but we're אנוס onus or, you know, שב ואל תעשה עדיף,
shev v'al ta'aseh adif, then all you get is one פרום frum
guy who thinks oh no, nobody's seeing me or whatever, I'm going
to go tear down this statue of Caesar or Zeus or whatever,
it ain't going to be good for the Jews, okay? So actually
there becomes like this almost tacit point of just like blocking that,
you know, bracketing that whole thing. The real problem is now in
Israel that we have power and we're not a minority religion and
some people want to draw on that to actually, you know, adopt
some very anti-democratic principles. I actually spoke about that the last few
weeks when I was in Israel about those issues. Anyway, so the
whole discussion here about this is about what do we do with
their objects of worship in terms of are we permitted to derive
benefit? But never like, oh, are we now obligated to destroy it?
Okay? So it is very certainly like, you know, worth sort of
mentioning that. And maybe again, maybe that's why it's okay to speak
about הנכרים Hanochrim and not העכו"ם Ha-akum because at the end of
the day we're just talking about whether we want to use it,
not whether we have to do something, you know, to it in
order to destroy it. Yes.
So in the Roman Empire idols were everywhere. Right? But in Persia,
the Persians were not big into building idols.
Right, but this is... right. But all the משניות mishnayos are start
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel and then the discussion sort of follow
from there. Okay, so let's take a look. הנכרים העובדים את ההרים
ואת הגבעות. Hanochrim ha'ovdim es heharim v'es hagevaos. So if you have
these non-Jews who worship the mountains and the hills, okay? הן מותרין,
hein mutarin, you can derive benefit from the mountains, you can go
and have a picnic on this mountain even though the pagans come
and worship on it. You can go ahead and, you know, dig
up some dirt and, you know, mine it for ore, okay? ומה
שעליהן אסורין. u'mah she'aleihen asurin. But
if there were some type of a thing on them, let's say
they plated the mountain with silver or something like that, you know,
and then as a way of honoring this because they believed it
was their god, okay, then you could not actually get benefit from
that silver that was on that mountain.
Meaning you couldn't sit on the mountain
either on the silver if you sat on it. You couldn't sit
on the silver. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it says, לא תחמוד כסף וזהב
עליהם, lo sachmod kesef v'zahav aleihem, do not covet the gold and
silver. On them, so the stuff on it remains forbidden even if
the thing itself is permissible. Now, how do we know the thing
itself is permissible? According to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, that's not
explicit, as I said. The idea here is it's part of the
landscape. Excuse me, you do not, you, Mr. non-Jew, do not have
the ability to say, I'm going to worship the entire earth as
my עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. And now what? Now I can't go
ahead? Mother Earth. Okay, I'm a real pagan, Gaea or whatever the
name is, Gaea is it? Yeah, what? Anyway, you know, you don't
have that ability. It's the landscape, you know. So A, you don't
have the ability because it's not fair to everybody else, like you
don't have the right, it's not yours to whatever. Of course, you
know, maybe if maybe I can worship my own plot of land
if I own it. So it's more than just that, it's also
that, you know, your acts define the identity of something and if
it's like it's sort of like why sticks and stones are מוקצה,
muktzah, because if they haven't yet come under human control, right, they're
not yours to define yet, they're just part of the landscape. So
your words and your actions, you know, if you dig it out
and you physically control it, so anyway you can't make it forbidden,
presumably that's implicit. It focuses on what's on it, not on the
thing itself, and therefore the thing on it is forbidden but it
itself remains permissible. שנאמר לא תחמד כסף וזהב עליהם. She'ne'emar Lo tachmod
kesef v’zahav aleihem. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר, Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer, רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili has a clear פסוק. passuk. He doesn't
relate to the gold and silver on it, he has a clear
פסוק passuk about why the mountains are permissible. שנאמר אומר אלוהיהם על
ההרים, She'ne'emar omer eloheihem al he'harim, their gods that are on the
mountains, ולו ההרים אלוהיהם, ve'lo he'harim eloheihem, but the mountains cannot become
their god, okay? So when it speaks about destroying their gods that
are upon the mountain tops, fine, the gods can be on the
mountain tops, but the mountain tops are not gods. אלוהיהם על הגבעות
ולא הגבעות אלוהיהם, Eloheihem al ha'gevaot ve'lo ha'gevaot eloheihem, same thing about
the hills. ומפני מה אשרה אסורה, U'mipnei mah asherah asurah, and if
that's true, then why is an אשרה asherah forbidden? Because isn't that
part of the ground, part of the earth and so on? Okay,
and it also says,
and it also says that you should destroy תחת כל עץ רענן.
tachat kol etz ra'anan. One way of understanding it is isn't that
just part of the ground? The other point is a textual point.
It says you should destroy אלוהיהם על ההרים eloheihem al he'harim what
does ותחת ve'tachat I can't remember the entire פסוק. passuk. But anyway,
אבד תאבדון Abbed te'abbedun whatever, anyway, אבד תאבדון abbed te'abbedun ותמחה שמם
מן המקום ההוא, u'temasheh shemam min ha'makom ha'hu,
whatever, anyway, there's too many פסוקים, pessukim,
ואבדתם את שמם מן המקום ההוא, ve'ibbadetem et shemam min ha'makom ha'hu,
whatever,
anyway, so why don't we say what's under the leafy tree is
forbidden but the leafy tree itself is permissible? Okay, so why then
is an אשרה asherah forbidden? מפני שיש בה תפיסת יד אדם וכל
שיש בה תפיסת יד אדם אסור, Mipnei she'yesh bah tefissat yad adam
ve'chol she'yesh bah tefissat yad adam assur, because that is something that
actually you have control over. Why do you have control over? Because
trees are planted. Now, not every tree is planted. Sometimes trees... Right,
so the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss that issue. Does it
mean that the ability to plant a tree and the fact that
naturally it is something we plant or whatever and things we control,
we uproot them and we replant them and so on, that always
means that they're seen as more under human control? Or we're speaking
about specifically a tree that we actually did plant? Okay, but anyway,
but that's why, because there are explicit verses that say destroy the
אשרה. asherah. So we've got a question: why destroy the אשרה asherah
if we don't destroy the mountain top? And the line of distinction
for him is because אשרה asherah is things that are physically controlled
by humans.
He's also saying that if like let's say there was an אשרה
asherah and I carved it into to be...
Yeah, that's but that's an easier case.
Okay, אמר רבי עקיבא אני אבין ואדון לפניך כל מקום שאתה מוצא
הר גבוה וגבעה נשאה ועץ רענן דע שיש שם עבודת כוכבים. Amar
Rabbi Akiva ani avin ve'adun lefanecha kol makom she'attah motze har gavoha
ve'givah nissa'ah ve'etz ra'anan da she'yesh sham avodat kochavim. Let me explain,
says Rabbi Akiva. The reason it says תחת כל עץ רענן, tachat
kol etz ra'anan, this is the way רש"י Rashi explains what Rabbi
Akiva is saying. Because here's the point, the same way you say
אלוהיהם על ההרים, eloheihem al he'harim, okay,
and
but that means that their gods are on the mountains but the
mountains aren't their gods, then it also says תחת כל עץ רענן.
tachat kol etz ra'anan. So why don't we say it means that
under the trees is their gods but the trees aren't their gods?
But we know that's not true, because another פסוק passuk says ואשריהם
תשרפון באש. ve'ashereihem tisrefun ba'esh.
So one answer is is that okay, this is actually telling you...
Well, one answer is it's not clear what this is doing, okay,
what תחת כל עץ רענן tachat kol etz ra'anan is doing. It's
just telling you, yes, you do destroy those אשרות, asherot, don't read
this פסוק passuk the way it is to say that the אשרה
asherah is permissible. And what's the difference? The difference is is that
what do you call it, is that תפיסת יד אדם. tefissat yad
adam. But Rabbi Akiva says okay, but then what is this פסוק
passuk saying? תחת כל עץ רענן, Tachat kol etz ra'anan, what's its
point? If it's not coming to tell you that the אשרה asherah
is permissible. So the point of this is to tell you, if
you want to know where to go looking for their עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, go look on the mountains and under the leafy trees.
Okay, that's where you'll find their עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So it's
actually just giving you like a map. Hey, you're going to go
into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you've got to get rid of the
idols, you know where they are? Go look at beautiful vistas and
leafy trees, that's where you'll find their idols. But not to suggest
that the tree itself is permissible.
Right, but isn't that in the פסוק, passuk, אבד תאבדון את כל
המקומות אשר עבדו שם הגוים? Abbed te'abbedun et kol ha'mekomot asher avedu
sham ha'goyim? I understand, right. ואבדתם את שמם מן המקום ההוא, Ve'ibbadetem
et shemam min ha'makom ha'hu, I guess he's saying that kind of...
Exactly. Okay, all in one point.
Right, right. Now, I want to say that there's a big debate
of רש"י ותוספות, Rashi ve'Tosafos, an interesting conceptual debate of what does
this mean when we say the mountains aren't forbidden. but the things
that are on them are. And this is like great, like לומדות,
lomdus, you know? So there's two basic approaches. Actually, רש''י Rashi has
both versions. One version is, the guy worships the mountain, is the
mountain halachically defined as an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but he doesn't
have the right to make it forbidden in benefit? But this mountain
is still an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Or do we say, no,
because he can't even define it as an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
like it's so out of your control that no matter how much
you worship it, you don't get to designate that this is an
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So is it that it's an עבודה זרה
avodah zarah but it's not forbidden in benefit? You don't have to
have, you're not entitled to have those consequences that people should have
to now not be able to use it, but your act defines
it as an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Or your act doesn't even
define it. Now, what are the reasons to think that your act
does define it as an עבודה זרה avodah zarah is the גמרא
Gemara says that somebody who bows down and worships a mountain has
done an
act
of עבודה זרה avodah zarah and yet put to death. But
that doesn't fully answer the question, because now it becomes a really
interesting issue about
calling it by a name?
No, it becomes an interesting issue in הלכה halacha about why things
become forbidden. Things become forbidden, you know, it's very, this segment that
we're learning is very what I will call חפצא chefza oriented, object
oriented, okay? Actually, it brings me back to my computer days, there
was something called object oriented
computer languages, whatever, it doesn't matter. Anyway, process oriented and object oriented,
it's total Brisker לומדות. lomdus. Anyway, the point is that for something
to become forbidden in benefit, you have to say that as an
object this is identified as an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. And now,
if I'm going to let's say offer this as an offering to
this עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, if I just make something like as
an offering to Zeus up in the sky, it might not make
it a תקרובת עבודה זרה, tikrovet avodah zarah, because the only way
something becomes אסור assur is you have to start with like, you
know, the עבודה זרה avodah zarah itself, the object itself which is
forbidden in benefit, and then things that attach themselves to it, נוי,
noy, תקרובת, tikrovet, תשמישים, tashmishim, by connection get the איסור הנאה issur
hana'ah as well. Okay, but just to offer something to the gods
maybe is not because there's no
object to Zeus in the sky? It's different than offering to a
Zeus statue in front of you.
Right, if you offer to Zeus in the sky, you would be
חייב מיתה, chayav misa, but the object might not be אסור בהנאה,
assur be-hana'ah, whereas if you offer to the statue in front of
you, it would be אסור בהנאה assur be-hana'ah and חייב. chayav. So
the point is that somebody could go ahead and say worship this
mountain and be חייב chayav in מיתה misa because they're worshiping something
that to some degree is an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but the
mountain we're not prepared to call a חפצא דעבודה זרה, chefza de-avodah
zarah, so therefore things offered to it might not be forbidden in
הנאה hana'ah and so on. Becomes all these interesting questions. Of course,
you know, תוספות Tosfos says, wait, that doesn't make sense. Like, if
you're offering to Zeus in the sky, we could put you to
death, that's an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But if you're offering, but
if you're doing a worship to the mountain, and we're not calling
the mountain an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, then it's not just that
the objects don't become forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, then you're not worshiping
to, you're not worshiping to a god in the sky and you're
not worshiping to a thing called an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So
it becomes all these long תוספות Tosfoses are all trying to sort
of figure this out. Like, what does it mean that the thing
is not forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, but, you know, is that saying
it's an עבודה זרה avodah zarah but it's not forbidden in הנאה?
hana'ah? That would explain why the gold on it is forbidden, because
once you're calling it an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you can make
the gold on it forbidden, you can say acts of worship are
forbidden. It's easier to explain the related things that are forbidden by
calling the mountain עבודה זרה avodah zarah and just say technically there's
no איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah. So תוספות Tosfos is inclined to say
that, because that explains why the gold on it is forbidden, why
acts of worship are forbidden. It's harder to say the mountain isn't
even called an עבודה זרה avodah zarah and somehow גזירת הכתוב gezerat
ha-katuv that the gold on it is אסור. assur. And, you know,
and then to say even though the mountain isn't an עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, if you worship it, you're חייב chayav for worshiping עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. Like, it's a lot harder. Anyway, so that's the
two opinions in רש''י, Rashi, two opinions in תוספות. Tosfos. Is the
mountain an עבודה זרה avodah zarah but there's no איסור הנאה? issur
hana'ah? That's the easier thing to say. Or is it not even
an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, and then you have to explain all
these other things that are still problems. Okay, so now let's look
at the גמרא. Gemara. דרבי יוסי הגלילי היינו תנא קמא. De-Rabbi Yose
Ha-Glili hainu Tanna Kamma. What is it? רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
Ha-Glili who quotes the פסוק pasuk אלוהיהם על ההרים, eloheihem al he-harim,
isn't he saying the same as the תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? So
אמר רמי בר חמא אמר ריש לקיש ציפוי הר כהר איכא
בינייהו. Amar Rami bar Chama amar Reish Lakish tzipui har ke-har ika
beineihu. Yeah, it's true, but the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma was clear
that the gold and silver is forbidden. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
Ha-Glili never says that, so that's the debate. תנא קמא סבר ציפוי
הר אינו כהר, Tanna Kamma savar tzipui har eino ke-har, that it's
not like the mountain. The mountain is permissible and the gold is
forbidden. ומיתסר u'mitasar and it's forbidden. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose Glili
סבר savar ציפויי הר הרי הוא כהר. Tzipuyei Har harei hu Kahar.
Since he doesn't make the דרשה drasha of gold and silver on
it, he would say once the mountain is not אסור בהנאה, assur
behana'ah, the gold and silver on it is also not אסור בהנאה.
assur behana'ah. Okay,
so that's a nice read like, yeah, but the תנא קמא Tanna
Kama learned from a פסוק pasuk that the gold and silver is
forbidden and רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose Glili doesn't learn that. רב
ששת אמר דכולי עלמא ציפויי הר אינו כהר. Rav Sheshet amar de'kulei
alma Tzipuyei Har eino Kahar.
Everybody says, everybody agrees with that point, that it's only that the
ground itself is permissible, okay, the gold and silver on it is
forbidden. והכא באילן שנטעו ולבסוף עבדו קמיפלגי. ve'hacha be'ilan shenata'o u'levasof avado
kamiflegi.
Here the issue is getting back to the אשרה, Asherah, let's say
you first planted a tree and then you worshipped it. תנא קמא
סבר אילן שנטעו ולבסוף עבדו מותר. Tanna Kama savar ilan shenata'o u'levasof
avado mutar. That actually it's permissible, okay, going in the opposite direction,
even though the gold and silver is forbidden, that's because gold and
silver at the end of the day is something... it's portable? Yeah,
it's something that's like a plating of the thing, it doesn't become
part of the landscape, it's not natural. But a tree that takes
root and becomes natural and part of the landscape, that's like ground,
and you can't make a ground forbidden, you can't make a tree
forbidden. Okay, if you planted it with the intent that this is
an אשרה Asherah tree, because תנא קמא Tanna Kama has to explain
when the תורה Torah says destroy the אשרה, Asherah, so that's a
tree that you planted to be an אשרה Asherah tree. But once
it was already growing and you worshipped it, you can't define it.
Or if you put it in like a pot that you can
move.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. תנא קמא סבר אילן שנטעו ולבסוף עבדו מותר. Tanna
Kama savar ilan shenata'o u'levasof avado mutar. רבי יוסי הגלילי סבר אילן
שנטעו ולבסוף עבדו אסור. Rabbi Yose Glili savar ilan shenata'o u'levasof avado
assur. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose Glili says no,
you can still make it forbidden. Now how do you get that
from רבי יוסי הגלילי? Rabbi Yose Glili? Okay, so we're going to
say that in a minute also, the גמרא's Gemara going to say
for him, just to give you a secret about what's coming, that
you don't make... if you planted it and worshipped it because even
for רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose Glili that's forbidden, the only thing
that's forbidden is what grows after you worshipped it. The thing that
already existed and took root and then you decided to come and
worship it, you can't define the thing that's already rooted into the
ground, that is part of the ground, but what you can make
forbidden for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is the stuff that grows afterwards.
Now where do you get this from רבי יוסי?
Rabbi Yose? Many like not like the three extra inches of branches.
Yes, exactly, the three extra inches of branches, yeah. Okay now, מאי,
mai, now where do you get this from רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose,
like why, who told you that? מדקתני סיפא מפני מה אשרה אסורה,
mi'de'katani seifa mipnei mah asherah asurah, why is an אשרה Asherah forbidden?
מפני שיש בה תפיסת יד אדם mipnei she'yesh bah tfisas yad adam
וכל שיש בה תפיסת יד אדם אסור ve'chol she'yesh bah tfisas yad
adam assur וכל שאין בה תפיסת יד... ve'chol she'ein bah tfisas yad...
He says that because when רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says what makes
an אשרה Asherah forbidden, that it has human sort of control, okay,
and anything that has human control is forbidden. So that broad statement
seems to be saying, you know, any degree of human control. He
didn't say an אשרה Asherah is forbidden, he could have said why
is an אשרה Asherah forbidden? Because it was planted initially with that
in mind. He didn't say that. He said anything that has human
control. Okay, so he says... וכל...? ve'chol...? מאי לאו לאתויי אילן שנטעו
ולבסוף עבדו, mai lav le'atuyei ilan shenata'o u'levasof avado, even a case
like this, ואף רבי יוסי בר יהודה סבר אילן שנטעו
ולבסוף עבדו אסור.
ve'af Rabbi Yose bar Yehudah savar
ilan shenata'o u'levasof avado assur.
This is also the position of רבי יוסי בר יהודה,
Rabbi Yose
bar
Yehudah, okay, if your
name is יוסי Yose then this is your position. דתניא רבי יוסי
בר יהודה אומר, de'tanya Rabbi Yose bar Yehudah omer, מתוך שנאמר אלהיהם
על ההרים, mitoch shen'emar eloheihem al he'harim, the gods on the mountain
tops, ולא ההרים אלהיהם, ve'lo he'harim eloheihem, but the mountains are not
their gods, אלהיהם על הגבעות ולא גבעות אלהיהם, eloheihem al ha'geva'ot ve'lo
geva'ot eloheihem, their gods on the hills and not the hills are
not their gods, שמעני תחת כל עץ רענן אלהיהם ולא עץ רענן
אלהיהם, shema'ani tachat kol etz ra'anan eloheihem ve'lo etz ra'anan eloheihem, maybe
I'll say the same thing under every leafy tree eloheihem, that their
gods are under the trees, ולא עץ רענן אלהיהם, ve'lo etz ra'anan
eloheihem, but the trees are not. This is exactly essentially what רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose Glili said and why don't I say the
extend that to say the trees are not עבודה זרה avodah zarah
as well? תלמוד לומר אשריהם תשרפון באש. talmud lomar ashereihem tisrefun ba'esh.
I can't say it because it says you have to destroy their
אשרות. asherot. Okay, by the way very relevant to פורים Purim because,
you know, scholars point out אסתר Esther and... עשתרה? Ashtarah? What's the
name? אישתר Ishtar and אשרה. Asherah. Anyway, fine. And מרדכי Mordechai was
מרדוך. Marduk. מרדוך. Marduk. Anyway, אלא תחת כל עץ רענן למה לי?
ela tachat kol etz ra'anan lamma li? So if that's true, what's
תחת כל עץ רענן tachat kol etz ra'anan tell me? ההוא לכדרבי
עקיבא, hahu le'che'd'Rabbi Akiva, it's like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דאמר רבי
עקיבא, de'amar Rabbi Akiva, אני אובין ואדין לפניכם, ani ovin ve'adin lifneichem,
כל מקום שאתה מוצא הר גבוה וגבעה נשאה ועץ רענן דע שיש
שם עבודה זרה. kol makom she'atah motzei har gavoah ve'geva nisa ve'etz
ra'anan da she'yesh sham avodah zarah. Okay, that's just to tell you
where to find the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Now what did רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose Glili say? He didn't say anything too interesting.
He basically said exactly what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose Glili said.
I mean this is רבי יוסי בר יהודה. Rabbi Yose bar Yehudah.
And the answer is yes, that's exactly the point. But since he
doesn't say that the difference between when is a tree forbidden and
when it's not forbidden is whether it was planted initially for that
purpose or not planted initially for that purpose, they could have drawn
the line there. And it didn't. It said no, the אשרות asherot
are always forbidden. And תחת כל עץ רענן tachat kol etz ra'anan
is just to tell you where to find the עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. So that sounds like even if it was not initially planted
for that purpose, it still becomes an עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But
it was still planted, it didn't say it grew on its own.
Okay, and then you started worshipping it. So then possibly not. Okay,
and that's a good point and then why not to discuss that
and that's also part of a discussion רש"י תוספות, Rashi Tosafot, so
let's just bracket that for now. Okay, so anyway the bottom line
is since both רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose Glili and רבי יוסי
בר יהודה Rabbi Yose bar Yehudah deal with the issue of trees
and they say why does a certain פסוק pasuk sound like it's
מותר mutar and they never... and they never draw a line between
saying whether it's planted initially or not planted, they basically come out
and say yeah all trees are אסור assur because of תפיסת יד
אדם, tfisas yad adam, that sounds like even if you planted it
and then worshipped it. It would still be a problem. Okay, now
Michael asked the scenario that I raised earlier, let's say it was
never planted at all, let's say it just grew wild. Okay, so
that's an important question, but we're going to bracket that. Are we
going to get back to it later? I don't know. Okay, but
that's my way of saying I'm not dealing with it now. ורבנן
האי ואשריהם תשרפון באש מאי עבדי ליה? V'rabbanan hai v'ashreihem tisrefun ba'esh
mai avdi lei? Now, according to the rabbis who basically say that
these types of things are permissible, so if trees are permissible, when
do you ever have to destroy the asherahs? Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says I already told you the answers to this. מיבעי ליה
לאילן שנטעו מתחילה לכך, Mibaye lei l'ilan sheneto m'techila l'kach, if it
was originally planted. So you have three scenarios, right? Originally planted, everybody
agrees. The חידוש chidush of רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili is
that even if it was first planted and then worshipped, that's enough
תפיסת יד אדם tfisat yad adam that you can still make it
forbidden. רבי יוסי בר יהודה נמי מיבעי ליה להא, Rabbi Yose Bar
Yehuda nami mibaye lei l'ha, but okay, everybody should agree that the
first point of trees would be assume you planted it for that.
How do you know to take it to the next stage and
say even if it was initially planted for other reasons and then
worshipped? אלא אילן שנטעו ולבסוף עבדו מנלן? Ela ilan sheneto u'levasof avdo
minalan? Okay, the asherah's פסוק pasuk is not enough to tell you
the scenario of first planted and then worshipped. Where would you learn
that from? נפקא ליה, Nafka lei, he learned it from ואשריהם תגדעון,
V'ashreihem tegadeun, that you should chop down the trees and not burn
their trees. So the difference is when you chop it down you
leave a stump. Okay, when you burn it you destroy it fully.
So there are two types of trees: ones you destroy fully, the
ones that were initially planted for that, and ones you chop down
and leave the stump, the ones that were planted and then you've
worshipped them. And then as I told you, only the stuff that's
forbidden is only the stuff that grows afterwards. So therefore, you can
chop it down and leave the stump. Why can't you just say
you cut it and then burn it, like the wood? Yeah, yeah,
but you're still leaving a stump. איזהו עץ שגידולו אסור ועיקרו מותר?
Eizehu etz shegidulo assur v'ikaro mutar? What type of a tree would
it be that the stuff you chop down would be forbidden and
you burn what you chopped down, but the stump you leave behind
is permissible? So where would this occur? הוי אומר אילן שנטעו ולבסוף
עבדו. Hevei omer ilan sheneto u'levasof avdo. Okay, it must be one
that was first planted. So now we clarify that for רבי יוסי
בר יהודה Rabbi Yose Bar Yehuda and רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose
HaGlili, even if it was already planted, the only thing you can
worship is what grows later, not what's original there. So you don't
have to cut the whole thing, leave a stump? You can cut
off all the stuff that grew later. Yeah, because the point is
you can't always exactly draw the line, like the stump will grow
wide, it's not just growing tall or whatever. Okay, it's all hypothetical.
Okay, and that by the way might be the answer to a
tree that grew naturally too, that as long as it's stuff that
grows later, that's seen as stuff that wasn't already there and stuff
that your actions have defined. So for the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
the only tree that's אסור, assur, any part of it is אסור,
assur, is if you planted it as an asherah. And for the
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, anything that grew afterwards is forbidden, and that's
the distinction of chopping down and burning. Burn is when it was
originally there, planted for an asherah. Chopping down is when it was
originally there first and then you worshipped it, and then only the
new stuff is forbidden. Let's just read one more line. Okay, if
you've got to go, that's fine, but I'm just going to do
one more line. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: הוי אומר
אילן שנטעו ולבסוף עבדו. Hevei omer ilan sheneto u'levasof avdo. והא ואשריהם
תשרפון באש כתיבי ותלמודא? V'ha v'ashreihem tisrefun ba'esh ketivei v'talmuda? But one
minute, how can you say that the idea of first planting it
and then worshipping it is from this verse of chopping down? He
quoted the verse of burning. Okay, so אילו לא נאמר קאמר. Ilu
lo ne'emar ka'amar. No, it means what's this תלמודא? talmuda? His learning,
his derivation was from the verse of burning. And you're saying that
his principle of having been already planted was from the verse of
chopping down. So the גמרא Gemara says אילו לא נאמר קאמר. Ilu
lo ne'emar ka'amar. No, it means had it not been for this,
I would have learned it from that. אילו לא נאמר תשרפון באש,
Ilu lo ne'emar tisrefun ba'esh, had it not been for the verse
of burning, הוה אמינא ואשריהם תגדעון באילן שנטעו מתחילה לכך. Hava amina
v'ashreihem tegadeun b'ilan sheneto m'techila l'kach. Chopping down would have meant that
it had originally been planted for that. השתא דכתיב ואשריהם תשרפון באש,
Hashta dechtiv v'ashreihem tisrefun ba'esh, because of the verse of burning, the
burning verse teaches me about trees that were originally planted. And therefore
that leaves extra the verse of chopping down for the חידוש chidush
of first planted and then worshipped. יאסר ליה ואשריהם תגדעון באילן שנטעו
ולבסוף עבדו. Yaser lei v'ashreihem tegadeun b'ilan sheneto u'levasof avdo. Okay, so
that's how he gets that even those trees are forbidden. Now by
the way I want to point out again, all this stuff, chopping
down, burning, destroying, burn, burn, anyway, you know, burn it, burn it,
that's Monty Python. Anyway, all of this is all just parenthetical to
learning that it's אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. Nobody is talking about actually
going and destroying this stuff. Okay, I just want to repeat that
point. ורבנן האי ואשריהם תגדעון מאי עבדי ליה? V'rabbanan hai v'ashreihem tegadeun
mai avdi lei? So since the rabbis say that the stuff that
grows after is permissible, what do they do with this verse of
chopping down that suggests part is forbidden and part is permissible? Okay,
לכי דרבי יהושע בן לוי, Lechi d'Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi, like Rabbi
Yehoshua Ben Levi. דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי: D'amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben
Levi: גידולי עבודת כוכבים קודמין לכיבוש ארץ ישראל כיבוש ארץ ישראל קודם
לביעור עבודת כוכבים. Gidulei avodat kochavim kodmin l'kibush eretz yisrael kibush eretz
yisrael kodem l'biur avodat kochavim. Done through three stages. When you go
in the land, you know, first just destroy all the obvious stuff,
do a quick raising of all the base עבודה זרה avodah zarah
and so on. After you, then conquer the land. Because while you're
in the process of conquering, you don't want to be seduced by
all the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. After you're done conquering, then you
can go back and really finish the job of... destroying it. So
the two ideas of chopping and burning are not to say that
there's some trees that the bottom is permissible and the top is
forbidden. Chopping is just saying first do the obvious chopping down, the
quick razing of it, R-A-Z-I-N-G, and then go back and fully destroy
it. That's the point. Okay. דתני רב יוסף DeTani Rav Yosef נתצתם
את מזבחותם Nitatztem et mizbechotam chop, destroy their altars, והנח vehaniach but
leave the rubble, don't initially get rid of the rubble. ושברתם את
מצבותם veshibartem et matzevotam again destroy their altars, והנח vehaniach and leave
it. והנח? Vehaniach? What do you mean leave it? סלקא דעתך? Salka
deitach? You think so? שרפו בנור! Sreifu banur! You gotta burn it!
So אמר רב הונא amar Rav Huna רדוף ואחר כך שרוף. redof
ve'acher kach srof. Right. First though, worry about the burning after you've
chased all of the Canaanite nations out of the land. So first
break, chase, destroy. Break, chase, destroy, burn, right, destroy. Okay, fine. So
that's what we learn out. But for the rabbis we learn out
that there's a bottom and a top, I mean for רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yossi, the bottom is permissible, the top is forbidden, even if
it was initially planted not related to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay.
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda האי סברא מנא ליה?
hai sevara m'nala lei? Where does he get this idea that there
are two stages? נפקא ליה מ-אבד תאבדון. Nafka lei mi'abeid t'abedun. Two
degrees of destroying, אבד abeid ואחר כך תאבדון. ve'acher kach t'abedun. First
initial destroying and then a full destroying. ורבנן האי מבעי ליה לעוקר
עבודה זרה שצריך לשרש אחריה. Verabbanan hai mibayei lei l'oker avodah zarah
shetzarich lesharesh achareha. No, that's to tell you even one step further.
Even after you've uprooted the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, עוקר oker it,
you have to now dig after its roots, לשרש אחריה. lesharesh achareha.
So there's three stages: chop it down, go back and destroy and
finish destroying it, and then go back and find out its roots.
It's very metaphoric. It's not enough to destroy it, you have to
get deep down and find the root of it to make sure
it doesn't sprout back. That could be even literal, right? If you
have a tree, it has deep roots. It starts literal, but it's
also metaphorical. Okay, so there's three stages. שצריך לשרש אחריה. shetzarich lesharesh
achareha. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה לשרש אחריה מנא ליה? Rabbi Yossi berabbi
Yehuda lesharesh achareha m'nala lei? So he must also hold of that,
where does he know it from? נפקא ליה מ-ואבדתם את שמם מן
המקום ההוא, Nafka lei mi've'ibadetem et shemam min hamakom hahu, completely destroy
their name. So not only cutting down, not only burning, but eradicate
their roots. So you actually have to literally go in there and
dig up all the roots? Apparently, yes. ורבנן ההוא לכנויי לה שם.
Verabbanan hahu lechanuyei lah shem. And the rabbis say ואבדתם את שמם
ve'ibadetem et shemam means that you have to have new names for
places. So you shouldn't call the place St. Louis or whatever it
is. You have to find new names to literally make it that
those are no longer the names that are used in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. In ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, so we got the
three levels: destroy, chop down, conquer the land, then go back and
burn and burn it, more fully destroy all of the remnants and
the rubble. And after you've destroyed the remnants and the rubble, then
dig out the roots. Okay, so we will continue with this tomorrow.
Are you able to actually look into that question about the art?
Yeah, it's been on my mind for many years, I've never really
found enough discussion of it. Okay, another joke in honor of פורים
Purim while everybody's packing up and going to דאווענען. daven. Okay, so
a guy walks out of Vatican City and sees these two people
there collecting alms. One is a person in a priestly garments with
a nice big gold cross and the collar and the whole thing
looking very distinguished and he's got this thing out there for alms.
And then there's this guy the Jew with the beard and tattered
clothes and the whole thing and he's there. So everybody walks out
of Vatican City, they spit at the Jew, I'm not talking about
spitting, they spit at the Jew and they give 20 bucks to
the priest, 50 bucks, 10 bucks, whatever, the Jew is getting nothing.
So finally some guy walks out and he says, he turns to
the Jew, says, I don't understand, he says, what are you doing
here? This isn't your place. Go to the Jewish quarter, collect alms
there, people will give you money. That's a way you'll raise money.
So the Jew looks up and the priest, he says, חיים, Chaim,
look who's telling us how to do business. Speaking of speaking of
priests, yes, nice little photograph of...